[Music]
hello and welcome to episode 5 of our
inventory tutorial series in this series
uh we're working on building an
inventory system but just to show you
where we're at at the minute we can
currently walk over items and we can
pick up items uh they they can stack and
once the stack's full so the tomatoes
got a maximum stack size of five it then
goes over to the next free slot and we
can pick up slots and we can move them
as we walk over an item it'll add itself
to the first stack that it's that has
some free space in it
and if the stack's full it'll just get
the first free slot on the inventory so
it'll go here when we pick up a tomato
and we can move them around and we can
pick up these potatoes which don't stack
and we can you know change the position
and they're actually changing in our
inventory here so
i'll place that down pick it up and we
can also pick them up and drop them out
of our inventory to delete the items
but what we can't do with the minute is
combine the stacks swap items or split
the stacks
which is what we're going to work to
which is what we're going to work
towards in this video
so let's just get started with that
straight away so if we go back over to
our inventory system um inventory
display class script
see that here's the two methods that we
you see that here's the two kind of
cases that we had for what happens when
a slot is clicked on and now we need to
see what happens when we take into
account some different kind of options
so for example what happens when both
slots have an item
we need to decide what to do because are
both items the same if so we want to be
able to combine them
if they're not we'll swap them can we
combine and can we actually combine the
stacks is that possible is the stack
full and how full is the stack so
we need to start working on this so the
first thing i'm going to do is we'll
account for swapping items because
that's the easiest to do first so
um
this is all kind of one
sort of this all kind of flows into each
other so we'll actually work on this
first
um
to do this i'm going to just come out of
this function and i'm going to make a
private void swap slots
and this is going to take in
um
the click to slot so inventory
slot ui clicked slot i'm doing this here
because we're going to use this function
twice up here so we may as well put it
into its own functions we're not
repeating
stuff
now to swap a slot
we need to clone
the mouse slot um
first because we need to make a copy of
the mouse slot so then when we move
what's on our hot hot bar to the mouse
would obviously lose what's on the mouse
then we couldn't put the mouse in the
empty slot so we need to make a cloned
kind of inventory slot
of the mouse's data so let's just do
variable
var cloned
slot or duplicate slot and this is just
going to make a new inventory slot
and it's going to take the mouse
inventory
item dot inventory
slot dot data
and it's gonna
hold the inventory slot
dot stack size
so we're just making a temporary
inventory slot that's not part of any
system it's just a sort of temporary
slot in this one function then it'll be
disposed of once we've used it
so now we can say mouse
inventoryitem.clearslot
because we've got a copy of it so we can
clear it
and now we can pass in
the clicked slots items we can update
the mouse slot and we can do click ui
slot dot assigned inventory slot
so this is what we're doing um
up here when we pick up an item so we've
copied what was on the mouse and then
we're picking up the item that was
currently in the slot
and then we want to clear the clicked
slot
because it's now on the mouse so we've
emptied the slot
and then we're doing what we did um
here
so we can actually just
copy this
paste it here but instead of the mouse
inventory slot we're going to pass in
the cloned slot
and let's just rename this to clicked ui
slot
clicked ui slot
so that's swapping items so
we have an item on the mouse we make a
copy of it then we clear the mouse off
put the click slot on the mouse and then
put the cloned
what was
then we put the copy of what was on the
mouse into the ui slot and then
you know this is disposed of once it
goes out of scope we won't it's just a
it's not used anymore so we don't need
it so let's just go back up here so the
first thing we want to do is so we need
to account for both um
items uh both the click slot and the
mouse having an item on it so we can
just copy this
paste it here
and we'll say not equal to null and not
equal to null so if the click slot has
an item and the mouse slot have an item
we now need to decide what to do so both
slots have an item decide what to do so
we need to see whether uh both slots uh
both items are the same
like is it are we trying to place a
tomato on a tomato or potato and a
potato etc or are we placing a potato on
a tomato for now let's just say if
clicked ui slot dot assigned inventory
slot dot item data
is not equal
to
the
mouse's inventory item data so if
they're not the same item
then we can just say swap slots
and we can pass in the clicked ui slot
so
call that there so now we should be able
to swap our potatoes and our tomatoes
let's hit play
so we can go over pick up some items and
we can pick up a potato and we'll swap
it for the tomato and we can put it back
down
now currently nothing happens with
the potatoes
we're not adding it so eventually you
know there's one potato here we have one
potato on the mouse we'll click and
they'll become two potatoes in that slot
but for now we can
now swap items we know our swap item
method is working so let's go back over
to our script
so we're back over in our
inventory display script
so let's start accounting for what
happens if the items are the same so
let's just copy this
so we want to say if
the clicked slots item is equal
to the mouse's inventory item
and
we want to check whether the clicked ui
slot
dot inventory slot
whether there's room left in the stack
and to check that we're going to pass in
the
mouse inventory item dot assigned
imagery slot dot stack size so so if
we've got three potatoes on the mouse
and we're trying to place them on top of
a potato that's in the
clicked ui slot the slot that we click
on is the room in that stack for the
amount of potatoes that we have on our
mouse and remember this is this
bool here so all it's doing is it's
checking whether the stack size plus the
amount to add
is less than or equal to the maximum
that that item can hold
so if we've got a stack size of three in
our inventory slot on our hotbar and
we're trying to add two that are held on
the mouse three plus two is equal to
five
which is less than or equal to the
maximum stack size which in this case is
five
if we tried to add three to a stack size
of three this would return false because
obviously um three plus three six which
is greater than the maximum stack size
so it would return
false
we can update our um stack sizes so we
can say
click ui slot dot assigned inventory
slot
and we can sign item
assign item
and let's assign the mouse i inventory
items
inventory
slot and let's just remind ourselves
what this function is doing
if we assign an item in this little
already has the item it's going to add
the stack to the stack size if it's not
the same item it'll just overwrite the
item so it'll swap the items around so
in this case we've already checked
whether the same item
and that the stack size won't go over
the maximum stack size so we can just
basically add to the stack that's
already there
with this item so we're assigning like a
tomato to the tomato so
they're the same so we're just going to
add them to the stack so then now
they've been assigned we can
call update ui slot on our
clicked ui slot
and then we need to clear our mouse
inventory item
because we've we've combined the items
now
so now we need to check whether there
isn't room left in the stack and if
there isn't we need to know how much
is actually left in the stack so we can
take it from our mouse so we'll do else
if we'll get this again
what i'm actually going to do is i'm
going to
get this and cut it and then up here i'm
gonna say bool
same
item or is
is same item
and we'll just put that there and then
we can just say here
is same item
and we can maybe bring this back up to
this line because it is quite a long
function
and the reason i've done that is because
we need this
again here so
else if if it's the same item
and
there isn't
room left in the stack
so this one is going to have to come
down because it's a long one so if the
click slot if there's no room left in
the stack
we need to get out
how much is left in the stack so left in
stack
so again let's just remind ourselves so
we've got two versions of this we've got
one where it doesn't pass it out because
we don't we don't need to know
but when it returns false we probably do
want to know how much is remaining so we
can say here out your max data stack
size
item data maximum stack size minus the
current stack size so if the max stack
size is five and we have three currently
this is going to return to
so here let's uh open up
our
curly braces so if it is the same item
and there's not room left in the stack
let's get out how much is actually left
in the stack
and we can actually just say if
left in stack is less than one
we can just swap the slots
passing in the clipped ui slot
so you know if if we have um so here
we've got a full stack so as we try and
combine them there's nothing left in the
stack so that'll be less than one
because it'll be zero and they they swap
and that's just to account for so here
we've got our two and we can place five
on this so instead of adding three to
this and leaving two on the mouse it
just swaps them because there's no point
you know messing around and adding it to
that stack just to leave them when we're
going to get the same result from
swapping them so
we can just swap them
directly so if left in stack is zero
which is essentially saying is the stack
full so let's just leave some notes here
so we
fully aware of what's going on so
and the stack is full so swap the items
and we'll do else
so else the
slot is not at max so slot is not at max
so take what's
needed
from the mouse inventory
so let's do int
remaining
on mouse
and we're going to say equals the mouse
inventory item dot inventory slot
assigned imagery slot
dot stack size minus left in stack
so if we've got five on the mouse
and there's
left in the stack is
on the click to slot is two this
remaining on mouse in would be three
because we've taken two from the mouse
to fill up the stack
so then we can say clicked ui slot dot
inventory slot we've got add to stack
i'm just going to pass in the amount we
want to add this time not just because
we already know that this the same item
we don't need to call assign item we can
just add to the stack directly
we can just pass in left in stack
and then click to ui slot dot update ui
slot
and then let's update the mouse with how
much is left remaining so we can say
variable new item
is equal to
a new inventory slot
with
the assigned inventory slots data and
our new
amount so remaining a mouse
then we'll clear the mouse slot
and then we'll update the mouse slot
with our new item then we can turn this
if into an else and attach it to
this whole statement so
if the item's the same
and there's room left in the stack let's
combine them
if the item's the same
and there's not room left in the stack
to take the full amount how much can it
take we're just checking whether it can
take less than one so the stack's full
and we'll swap them
think about it i don't know if that
would ever get called but you know it
works so
i'll check that well let's check that in
a second um but we're saying else let's
calculate how much would be remaining on
the mouse when we fill up the clicked ui
slot stack let's fill up the ui slot
stack and then let's make the mouse
inventory item
have the new amount
and else if they're not the same
so uh else
if
not is same
let's just swap the stars okay so back
in unity
we can't currently split the stack so
it's kind of hard to show this off but
what i can do is if i click our um
player
and i go over you can see that we've got
five five and one these are these
tomatoes i can change the inventory
amount directly so i can say it's three
in this one
two in this one
and then if i that won't update the ui
because i've manipulated them directly
so i'm gonna have to pick them up and
put them back down to get the correct
amounts in there so now we'll be able to
see
uh the combining of the items so we've
got
three tomorrow stacks here with all
different sizes i'm gonna add to the two
to the one so now there's three slots
we've combined them
three plus three would be six and the
maximum stack size is five so i'm going
to pick up the three
place two into this stack so now there's
five in that stack which is the maximum
amount and then we can put our one back
down and if we click it'll just swap
them
around because the stacks are full like
one of the stacks is full so
they won't combine
so
the last kind of implementation of this
is splitting the stacks and then we'll
be able to work on the chests and etc in
the next episode
so let's get the stack splitting working
let's go back over to
our inventory system in visual studio
okay so let's just come up here and type
in bool is
shift
pressed and we'll say this is equal to
keyboard
dot current dot left shift key
dot is pressed
so if the left shift key is pressed when
we um click on a slot this will be true
and if it's not it'll be false
this is using the new input system and
it's using it directly if you wanted to
use your input action asset and have it
so players can um
[Music]
change which key is the
split stack key you'll you'd have to do
that through the input action asset
and like maybe use like an input manager
we're just going to read it directly
here because this isn't an input system
tutorial it's a inventory system
tutorial if you want me to go over and
cover that in some more detail and
actually do some input system stuff let
me know in the comments below
but for now we'll just check it directly
and hard code it so it'll always be the
left shift key and it's here that we're
going to check
this and split the stack if um if
possible so
for now i'm just gonna say if
um is shift pressed
[Applause]
and then we're gonna um
and if it is then we'll split the stack
so we'll and split stack
i'll say else so if the shift key isn't
pressed
then we'll just pick up the item as we
have been doing
so to actually split the stack
we're going gonna make a method on our
inventory slot so we'll say if shift is
pressed and
clicked ui slot
dot inventory slot dot um split stack
which is a method that we're going to
make in a second so let's go and make
that
so let's go over to our
inventory slot class
and let's just uh
let's come down here and we'll do a
public and this is going to be a ball
because it's going to return false if we
can't actually split the stack for
example if there's just one item
we won't be able to split it
so we're going to say public ball split
stack and this is going to pass out
a new inventory slot because it's going
to have
a new inventory slot with the split
amount already in it so we could say
out inventory slot split stack
so let's just start defining this so
if
stack size
is
less than
or equal to one
then we're just going to return
null
and we're just going to return false
and split stack will be equal to null
but if it is greater than one so if
there's multiple items in stack and we
can we can successfully uh split them
let's just calculate how much half the
stack actually is so we'll do half stack
equals i'm going to do math f dot round
to int
and we'll do um stack size divided by
two
then we'll take half the stack size off
this amount so
let's just use our
remove from stack function and we'll
pass in the half stack size
so we're going to take
half the stack off the current stack
we're then going to split uh set the
split stack
equal to a new inventory slot
with the item data and the half stack
amount in
so if we have
four and we've
held down shift and clicked we're gonna
split the stack it's gonna split the
stack from four divided by two so the
half stack would be two
we'll remove two from
the four that we currently have in the
stack
and then we'll make a new inventory slot
with
two of the same item in it
and we'll pass that back out to our
inventory
display so we can say out
inventory slot and this is the half
stack slot
so we can put
the
so here we know there's nothing on the
mouse so we can just update the mouse
slot
with our half stack
and we because we've changed the
slot directly on the clicked slot we can
just update the ui and this will check
for its new amount and it'll refresh it
and then we can just return
because we're done we don't need to
carry on
and just to be kind of consistent
we can
put our returns in elsewhere
it won't matter too much but let's just
return once we get to those kind of
key points because there's no point
trying to process the rest of the code
because we have separate if statements
so it'd return and then it'd try and do
this and
it'd be confusing so we just need to
return out of them
that should be our split stack oh we're
not uh we need to return true here
return true there because we
successfully split the stack so let's go
back over to unity
make sure we've cleared the log make
sure there's no errors let's hit play
so we can now pick up loads of tomatoes
and we've got two here we can hold down
shift and click and we can pick up one
place the one down we can combine them
back together
we can hold down shift
split the stack so we'll take two from
it because we've rounded up
we can click again
we can add two to two four to one
they'll swap
two there let's split them again
so let's pick up the potatoes if we hold
down shift it'll just pick up the slot
because it'll just pick up the potato
because we can't split one so it'll just
pick it up
place it back down we can't combine
these items because the maximum stack
size is one
and once the inventory is full
it won't put pick up any more items
unless it can add them to an existing
stack
and we can clear our inventory of all of
the potatoes
and start picking more up
so i think that's a good place to leave
this video all of the
core functionality of manipulating the
inventory is now done
what we're going to work on in the next
video is
the ability to access the chests
so you see in my test project as i walk
up to a chest i can press a button on
the keyboard and the inventory window
pops up i can place uh items in it
and close the inventory come over to
this chest
it's a smaller chest there's less
inventory slots assigned to it you can
put in five hearts there we can go back
to this chest and this chest has its
inventory
system all set up and ready to go
we can take them back out
and we've got the same sort of
functionality as well so we can put them
in and we can split them here and then
we can take one out leave one in
come pick up the
this item you know try and put them in
it'll swap
and it'll put we can put them back over
here
so yeah that's what we'll work towards
in the next video
as always if you're watching these
videos as they go out the full series is
already up over on patreon which is
patreon.com forward slash danpas as well
as all of the videos i'm exporting
packages each at the end of each episode
with the script so if you need to follow
along and you want the um and you want
the code to check against yours you can
get that by subscribing over on patreon
if you do have kind of any issues and
you want them you want some help let me
know in the comments below um the best
place to help is probably the discord
though there is a an invite to the
discord in the description box because
you can post uh code snippets there and
it's a bit easier to share links to
stuff um than a youtube comments and
it's a bit more real time
so if you do need any help i recommend
going over to the discord but in the
meantime thanks for watching and i'll
see you in the next one bye
you